Inventory of the Martha Barksdale Papers, ca. 1918-1974.
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Martha Barksdale Papers, ca. 1918-1974.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Archives Acc. 1985.54
1.5 linear feet.
Martha Barksdale was a member of the first class of women to graduate from the College of William and Mary in 1921, and taught physical education at William and Mary from 1921 to 1966. Her papers include her diary, 1918-1919, and photographs of women's athletics and other student activities.
Martha Elizabeth Barksdale
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Biographical/Historical Information
Martha Elizabeth Barksdale (1899-1974) was a member of the first class of women to graduate from the College of William and Mary, entering in 1918 and receiving her Bachelor of Arts degree in 1921. She also received a Master of Arts degree from William and Mary in 1929. She taught physical education at William and Mary from 1921 until her retirement in 1966. She was the first woman tapped into the Virginia Alpha Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa.
Scope and Content Information
The papers include Martha Barksdale's diary for 1918-1919, recording her experiences as a member of the first class of women at William and Mary. The bulk of the collection consists of photographs that document student activities and women's sports at the college from her student years throughout her teaching career. The bulk of the photographs date from the 1920s-1940s.
Index Terms
Persons:
Barksdale, Martha Elizabeth.; Chamings, Dorothy Thurza Louise, d. 1958.
Subjects:
College of William and Mary--History--20th century.; Intramural sports.; Women--History-- Virginia.; Athletics--Study and teaching.; Athletics--United States.; College sports--United States- -History--20th century.; College sports--Virginia--Williamsburg.
Contents List
- Diary of Martha Barksdale, 1918-1919. (Box-folder 1:1-2)
  In her diary, Martha Barksdale recorded the events of her first year at college, as a member of the first class of women to enter the College of William and Mary.
  Original diary in Box 1, folder 1; photocopy and transcription in Box 1, folder 2.
- Gymnastic Peoples College Diploma, 1926. (Box-folder 1:3)
  The diploma, from Gymnastic Peoples College in Ollerup, Denmark, reads: "Martha Elizabeth Barksdale has successfully completed the six weeks summer course for American women teachers of physical education and is hereby endorsed as an exponent of fundamental gymnastics in America."
- Faculty information form, 1938., 2 pages. (Box-folder 1:4)
  Completed form for Martha Barksdale giving her department and title; degrees held and other education; date and place of birth and parents' names; clubs and fraternities; publications; hobbies; teaching experience; other positions held.
- Photo albums. (Box 1)
  Photo album (gift to Florrie in 1892) filled with cartes de visite and cabinet cards; photo album containing black-and-white photos of family, friends, and farm scenes, ca. 1910s-1920s.
- Autograph book of Dorothy Chamings, 1926-1927. (Box 1)
  Signed by Dorothy's high school friends.
- Photographs, College of William and Mary. (Box 2-3)
  Each subject folder contains one or several black-and-white photographs. Almost all are of college activities and people, especially women's athletics. They range in date from 1918 to around 1970, but most date from the 1930s-1950s.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject, with one or several photographs per subject folder. Box 2 contains "Athletics--Fencing" to "Women's Baseball." Box 3 contains "Women's Basketball" to "Women's Track."
  - Athletics--Fencing
  - Barksdale, Martha
  - Bland, Tommy
  - Briscoe, Marjorie Jane
  - Christmas Activities
  - Dances
  - Freshman Class of 1918
  - Gibbons, Frances Louise
  - Groggins, Jane
  - Group Photos--unidentified
  - Harwood, Bessie Virginia
  - H2E Club
  - Homecoming
  - Individual Photos--unidentified
  - J. Lesslie Hall Literary Society
  - Jessup, Bettie Sue
  - May Day
  - Men's Gymnastics
  - Mitchell, Dorothy Reis
  - Moss, Mattie Edna
  - Orchesis (Dance Club)
  - Reeder, Marion
  - Song Contest
  - Terrell, Dorothy
  - Torrence, Beatrice
  - Visitors to Campus--Coolidge, Calvin (1926)
  - Women's Apparatus Club
  - Women's Archery
  - Women's Archery--Intramural
  - Women's Athletic Committee
  - Women's Athletic Council
  - Women's Athletics--Administration
  - Women's Badminton--Intramural
  - Women's Baseball
  - Women's Basketball
  - Women's Basketball--Intramural
  - Women's Bowling--Intramural
  - Women's Bridge--Intramural
  - Women's Bridge--Tournament
  - Women's Canoeing
  - Women's Coaches
  - Women's Field Hockey
  - Women's Field Hockey--Intramural
  - Women's Gymnastics
  - Women's Horseshoes--Intramural
  - Women's Intramural Council
  - Women's Lacrosse
  - Women's Lacrosse--Intramural
  - Women's Life Saving
  - Women's Monogram Club
  - Women's Ping Pong--Intramural
  - Women's Soccer
  - Women's Student Council
  - Women's Swimming
  - Women's Seimming--Intramural
  - Women's Sports Teams
  - Women's Tennis
  - Women's Tennis--Intramural
  - Women's Track